A Guide to the Papers of Samuel Leyens Switzer, 1910-1957
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Old Dominion University
The Papers of Samuel Leyens Switzer 1910-1957
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Old Dominion University
MG 37
Five hollinger document cases and three oversize boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
On loan from Mrs. Bettie Minette Cooper, March 20, 1980; last accession August 15, 2005.
Biographical Information
Samuel Leyens Switzer was born into a prominent family in Vicksburg, Mississippi, on November 26, 1896. He was a son of Simon and Flora Leyens Switzer. In 1902, Sam's father died, leaving his widow Flora with four children: Louis, Minette, Barbara and Samuel. Samuel Switzer's correspondence begins when he journeyed North in 1911 to complete his secondary education at Phillips Exeter Academy in Exeter, New Hampshire. After Exeter, Sam entered Harvard University in Cambridge, Massachusetts, as a member of the class of 1918. Sam's letters home during this period reveal that he was a typical college student interested in fashions, football, girls and grades.
While attending college Samuel Switzer joined Harvard University's Military Reserve Unit. After his sophomore year, in the summer of 1916, Sam attended and successfully completed a United States Army training camp in Plattsburgh, New York. Sam returned to Harvard University in the fall of 1916, continuing both his studies and his military training. The United States entered World War I on April 6, 1917. Sam spent the summer of his junior year, from May 7 to August 15, 1917, in a military instruction camp of the War Department of the United States at Harvard University. Throughout the summer of 1917, the situation in Europe worsened for the Allies and Sam decided to sacrifice his senior year at Harvard University for his country.
In August 1917 Sam Switzer entered Officer's Training Camp at Leon Springs, Texas. On November 27, 1917, he was commissioned a First Lieutenant in Field Artillery. Lieutenant Switzer completed his military training with the Tenth Field Artillery, Third Division, at Camp Douglas, Douglas, Arizona. Sam drilled throughout the winter of 1918. On April 23, 1918, Lieutenant Samuel Switzer sailed with his Division for France. After a field artillery course at Coetquidau, France, Sam Switzer participated in the Champagne-Marne defensive (July 15, 1918), the Marne-Aisne offensive (July 18 - August 2, 1918), the Saint-Mihiel offensive (September 12 - 14, 1918), and the Meuse-Argonne offensive (September 26 - November 11, 1918).
Lieutenant Switzer was cited in the General Orders Headquarters of the Third Division, American Expeditionary Forces, for gallantry in action. His " brave work in defending a position near a bridge in the vicinity East of Chateau Thierry on July 14, 1918 " entitled him to wear the Distinguished Service Cross. Lieutenant Switzer's bravery so impressed the staff of the United States Field Artillery Journal that they requested an account of his experience defending the gun at Mezy Bridge. Unfortunately, Mr. Switzer never found the time to fulfill their request.
After the Armistice was signed on November 11, 1918, Lieutenant Switzer traveled through Luxembourg and into Germany. He remained in Kretz and Kruft, Germany, with the American Army of Occupation. In March 1919 he was detailed to the American Expeditionary Forces University at Beaune, Cote d'Or, France. Lieutenant Switzer was " relieved from assignment and further duty in the Army " while a student at the American Expeditionary Forces University.
At Beaune University he studied French, political science and business law. In May 1919, while still in France, Sam Switzer was awarded his A.B. degree in absentia from Harvard University. He was awarded this degree as a student who had completed three-fourths of the requirements but was unable to complete the entire course due to military service.
On June 15, 1919, Sam Switzer sailed for home with the St. Aignan Special (Beaune University) Casual Company Number 6438. After his arrival in New York City, Lieutenant Switzer proceeded to Fort Shelby, Mississippi, where he was formally discharged from the United States Army on July 29, 1919.
As a civilian, Sam Switzer entered the family business in Vicksburg, Mississippi. The Switzer family owned The Valley Dry Goods Company, the largest department store in the Mississippi Valley. As president of The Valley, Samuel Switzer remained one of Vicksburg's most eminent businessmen. He was active in all phases of civic life and was a devoted member of Anshe Chesed congregation, having served as congregation president and for a number of years as president of the Young Men's Hebrew Association. He was former chairman of the Jewish Welfare Federation and was a member of B'nai B'rith.
Sam Switzer was also a member of the Vicksburg Kiwanis Club, the Chamber of Commerce, and the board of directors of the Vicksburg Country Club. In addition, Mr. Switzer was a member of the American Legion and the Vicksburg Library Board.
After World War I Sam Switzer maintained contact with his military comrades through correspondence and attendance at the Tenth Field Artillery's reunion conventions. He also indulged his passion for travel. In the summer of 1937 he took a trip around the world. He also made numerous trips to Europe and Iceland. He was an enthusiastic philatelist and amateur photographer. A lifelong bachelor, Samuel Leyens Switzer died on April 14, 1960, in Vicksburg, Mississippi. His family remembered him as being " fervently American as a nationality and Jewish as a religion. "
Scope and Content
The papers of Samuel Leyens Switzer are a collection of personal papers, official correspondence, and maps, dating from 1910-1957, the bulk of which dates from 1911 to 1920. The collection is divided into six series: correspondence, literary productions, printed material, maps, photographic material, and memorabilia.
Series description and arrangement
Series I: Correspondence - constitutes the vast majority of the materials in the collection. Correspondence is arranged in chronological order by month and year. Incoming and outgoing correspondence is filed together. Letters, telegrams, postcards and address books are included in this series. The principal value of the papers is in the extensive correspondence of the World War I period. This includes his college years at Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts. He often wrote long and very detailed letters concerning his daily actions. His letters reveal the life of an average college student. His military training at camps in Plattsburgh, New York, Leon Springs, Texas, and Douglas, Arizona, are also vividly described. He amply chronicled his personal experiences as a Lieutenant in the Artillery of the American Expeditionary Forces in France and Germany during World War I, for the folks back home. Particularly moving are the letters describing the final days of the war before the Armistice, the long march into Germany and the early months of the Occupation. Correspondence after 1920 is sparse. It is largely limited to military matters and is impersonal in nature. The correspondence is also valuable for the bits of social history that are revealed for the careful reader. Popular slang terms, a description of a hurricane, prejudices and fears, reactions to new inventions like the automobile are evident. Finally, the collection provides a glimpse into the successful life of a young American in college, the military and a Southern city at the turn of the century.
Series II: Literary productions - includes an early composition of young Sam Switzer and the syllabus and class notes from a course in Contemporary International Relations. He took this course at the American University in Beaune, France, from March to June 1919.
Series III: Printed materials - consists of legal documents; lists; bulletins/orders; programs; certificates; identification cards; newspaper and magazine clippings; books; sections of newspapers; magazines and journals. These materials span the years from 1916 to 1928. Military matters take precedence in this series.
Series IV: Maps - date from the World War I era. All of the maps deal with areas of Europe and most of them are in French and German. Several maps detail battle positions and troop movements in World War I.
Series V: Photographic material - includes positive prints and a large collection of postcards all dating from the World War I period. Postcards are filed by country and city. The countries represented include France, Germany, Monaco, Spain, and Italy. Postcard packets of the destruction at Verdun and La Marne are also part of the collection.
Series VI: Memorabilia - consists of various items such as Switzer's diploma and certificate from Harvard, his diploma from Exter academy, and his International Dateline Certificate from Pan American World Airways.
Index Terms
Switzer, Samuel Leyens, 1896-1960; World War, 1914-1918--Biography; Harvard University--Biography; Correspondence; Maps; Photographs; Memorabilia
Contents List
- Correspondence 1911-1957
  - Schooling: Exeter, New Hampshire November 1911 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Schooling: Exeter, New Hampshire 1911 - 1914 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Schooling: Exeter, New Hampshire February 1914 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts September 1914 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts October 1914 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts November 1914 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts December 1914 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts January 1915 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts February 1915 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts March 1915 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts April 1915 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts May 1915 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts March 1916 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts April 1916 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Military Training: Plattsburgh, New York June 1916 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Military Training: Plattsburgh, New York July 1916 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - New York City August 1916 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts October 1916 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts March 1917 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts April 1917 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - College: Harvard University, Massachusetts May 1917 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Military Training: Harvard's Reserve Unit June 1917 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Military Training: Harvard's Reserve Unit July 1917 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Military Training: Harvard's Reserve Unit August 1917 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Military Training: Leon Springs, Texas September 1917 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Military Training: Leon Springs, Texas October 1917 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Military Training: Leon Springs, Texas November 1917 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Military Training: Douglas, Arizona December 1917 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Military Training: Douglas, Arizona January 1918 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Military Training: Douglas, Arizona February 1918 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Military Training: Douglas, Arizona March 1918 (Box-folder 1:31)
  - New York City April 1918 (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Sailing to and arrival in France May 1918 (Box-folder 1:33)
  - World War I: France June 1918 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - World War I: France July 1918 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - World War I: France August 1918 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - World War I: France September 1918 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - World War I: France October 1918 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - World War I: France November 1918 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Occupation Army: Germany December 1918 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Occupation Army: Germany January 1919 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Occupation Army: Germany February 1919 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Occupation Army: Germany March 1919 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Beaune University: France April 1919 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Beaune University: France May 1919 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Beaune University: France June 1919 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Arrival in America and Discharge from the Army July 1919 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi November 1919 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi April 1920 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi August 1920 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi November 1920 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi March 1921 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi May 1921 (Box-folder 2:20)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi July 1921 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi December 1921 (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi January 1922 (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi March 1922 (Box-folder 2:24)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi September 1922 (Box-folder 2:25)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi October 1922 (Box-folder 2:26)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi November 1922 (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi April 1923 (Box-folder 2:28)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi May 1923 (Box-folder 2:29)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi July 1923 (Box-folder 2:30)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi November 1925 (Box-folder 2:31)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi December 1926 (Box-folder 2:32)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi December 1927 (Box-folder 2:33)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi February 1928 (Box-folder 2:34)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi March 1928 (Box-folder 2:35)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi April 1928 (Box-folder 2:36)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi February 1937 (Box-folder 2:37)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi March 1937 (Box-folder 2:38)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi June 1937 (Box-folder 2:39)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi July 1937 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi August 1937 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi September 1937 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi October 1937 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Vicksburg, Mississippi July 1957 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Undated Undated (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Address Books Ca. World War I (Box-folder 3:7)
- Literary Productions 1910, 1919
  - Composition 1910 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Syllabus and Notes from "Contemporary International Relations" March-June 1919 (Box-folder 3:9)
- Printed Material 1916-1928
  - Legal Documents, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Lists, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Bulletins/Orders 1916-August 1921 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Programs 1910-1928 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Certificates 1916-1922 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Identification Cards, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings Ca. World War I (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings Post-World War I (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Newspaper-The Vicksburg Herald (Vicksburg, Mississippi) May 14, 1916 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Newspaper-The Camp News(Plattsburgh, New York) July 8-August 5, 1916 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Newspaper-The Sunday Herald (Boston, Mass) May 6, 1917 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Newspaper-The Stars and Stripes (Paris, France) Jan. 17, 1919 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Newspaper-Fourth Corps Flare (Mayen, Germany) Jan. 17, 1919 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Military Books, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Abridged Prayer Book for Jews in the Army and Navy of the United States, ca. World War I (Box-folder 4:2)
  - A New World in the Making 1919 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - A Popular Geography of France, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 4:4)
  - In Flander's Field Ca. 1920's (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Magazine-Le Pantheon de la Guerre, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Magazine-Mid-Week Pictorial September 4, 1919 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Journal-The Field Artillery Journal March-April 1921 (Box-folder 4:8)
- Maps
  - Maps of Europe, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 4:9)
  - German and French WWI maps (11 German, 2 French), and 1 map of France (Item Box 1)
  - 11 French WWI era maps, 9 German WWI era maps, 1 English/American map of Pacific Territories, 1 map of Paris, 1 map of Pacific Ocean (National Geographic), and 1 map of the United States (National Geographic) (Item Box 2)
- Photographic Material 1917-1919
  - Positive Prints-Sam Switzer and Family (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Positive Prints-Harvard Training Camp Summer 1917 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Positive Prints-Camp Douglas, Arizona December 1917-April 1918 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Positive Prints-World War I 1918-1919 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Postcards-Camp Douglas, Arizona December 1917-April 1918 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Postcards-France, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Postcards-France: Verdun, La Marne, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Postcards-France: Lyon, Paris, Dole, Mont-Roland, Dijon, Langres, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Postcards-France: Marseille, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Postcards-France: Beaune, Cote D'Or, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Postcards-Germany: The Rhine, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Postcards-Germany: Metz, Kruft, Coblenz, Andernach, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Postcards-Monaco, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Postcards-Gibraltar, Spain, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Postcards-Rome, Italy, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Postcards-Vicksburg, Mississippi, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:16)
- Memorabilia 1914-1955
  - Memorabilia, Ca. World War I (Box-folder 5:17)
  - Diploma: Harvard University June 1918 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Certificate: Harvard University June 20, 1918 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - International Dateline Certificate, Pan American World Airways November 23, 1955 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Diploma: The Phillips Exeter Academy June 22, 1914 (Box-folder 3:4)